Glen van den Bergen

(+61) 4 12 047 642 contact@glenvdb.com

My career has been shaped by a keen interest in technology and an aptitude to learn new ways of solving problems with software. I have developed computational models, optimisation algorithms, data processing, analysis and visualisations. I understand the value of data and how it can inform evidence-based decision making. In the next phase of my career I want to apply these skills to solve challenges in data orchestration and model deployment to production systems, to deliver efficiency and value. In working with others I believe building trust and understanding needs, through patience and mutual respect, leads to productive outcomes.

During my free time when I'm not tinkering with projects on the Raspberry Pi or reading articles on news.ycombinator.com I'm either indulging my 3 year old son's obsession with dinosaurs at the museum, baking sourdough bread, putting on a batch of homebrew, or gardening.

EDUCATION

PHD CANDIDATE

UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND

Brisbane, Qld Apr 2016 – Oct 2019 In my research I used computer models and algorithms to optimise the properties of antimicrobial peptides to better understand their activity and selectivity on cellular membranes.

This required using a diverse technology stack for data analysis, evolution-based algorithms, and molecular dynamics computer simulations on Australian supercomputers from National Computation Infrastructure (NCI) and the Pawsey Supercomputing Centre. Parts of my research are available as online tools at atb.uq.edu.au/asp and atb.uq.edu.au/peg.

Research funded by grants from the Australian Research Council (ARC, DP160103414) and the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC, APP1044327) and a scholarship awarded by the Department of Industry, Innovation and Science.

UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND

MASTER OF BIOINFORMATICS

Brisbane, Qld Jan 2012 – Nov 2015 Studied theory and practice of biological sciences, including utilisation of software to analyse and organise biological data. Awarded the **Dean's Commendation for Academic Excellence** with a cumulative GPA of 6.75 out of 7.

Studied fundamental and advanced concepts in programming and software

Achievements include:

- Data Mining: High Distinction (7/7)
- Computational Statistics: Distinction (6/7)
- Bioinformatics courses: High Distinction (7/7)
- Research courses: High Distinction (7/7)

QUEENSLAND UNIVERSITY OF TECHNOLOGY

Brisbane, Qld

BACHELOR OF I.T. / BACHELOR OF COMMUNICATION DESIGN

engineering using Java and C/C++. Learned skills in illustration, animation (2D/3D), 3D modelling, and interactivity using multimedia software packages.

Jan 2002 – Nov 2006 Achievements include:

- Software Engineering Principles: High Distinction (7/7)
- Media Technology 2: Distinction (6/7)

WORK HISTORY

UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND

RESEARCH ASSISANT

Brisbane, Qld Aug 2015 – Apr 2016 Continued research from project for Masters of Bioinformatics on predicting structure of antimicrobial peptides using evolutionary algorithms to optimise amphipathicity. As an additional responsibility, updated and automated the API documentation of the Automated Topology Builder (atb.uq.edu.au) and developed web administration features.

SPEEDWELL

SENIOR TEST ANALYST

Brisbane, Qld Jun 2012 – July 2015 Defined, executed, and reported testing outcomes for web and smartphone applications via test plans, test cases, bugs reports, and fix verifications. Coordinated a team of offshore testers in Manila, Philippines and conducted team and professional development exercises.

GLOBAL X

SENIOR TEST ANALYST

Brisbane, Qld Aug 2011 – Jun 2012 Established software-testing and release practices within an Agile process using the Scrum framework. Performed requirements analysis of software systems and definition of acceptance criteria. Performed paired testing with software engineers during development for rapid turnaround on defect identification and resolution.

KROME STUDIOS

TECHNICAL WRITER

Brisbane, Qld Feb 2008 – May 2010 Documented features of in-house development tools for interactive entertainment including usage manuals and video tutorials. Worked closely with developers to document technical information in an accessible format for creatives.

KROME STUDIOS

SENIOR TEST ANALYST

Brisbane, Qld Nov 2006 – Feb 2008 Managed a team of testers on projects across multiple platforms to investigate interactive software, identify defects, record and manage defects, and report software quality to project managers.

'SOFT' SKILLS, KNOWLEDGE, AND EXPERIENCE

Leadership

While a Senior Test Analyst I lead a team of testers in Manila, Philippines. While in Manila I conducted professional development exercises. I cultivated a culture of independence, creativity and personal responsibility. During my PhD I mentored undergraduate and honours students, instilling in them the technical and conceptual skills required for their research.

Scrum + Agile development

I have worked on multiple software projects that implemented Agile development with the Scrum framework for iterative and adaptive software development; including sprint planning, daily stand-up, review, and retrospectives with clients, product owners, scrum masters, and developers.

Public speaking

I have strong presentation skills. I have presented talks and posters on my PhD research at local and international conferences in Edinburgh (UK), Dublin (Ireland), and Switzerland.

Cultural experience

Until I was six years old I grew up on Bougainville Island, 1000 km east of Papua New Guinea, and as a teenager I lived in Malaysia for two years. The time spent in these countries, and travelling abroad in my adulthood, has given me an abiding respect and appreciation for different cultures and perspectives.

TECHNICAL SKILLS, KNOWLEDGE, AND EXPERIENCE

Python and libraries

I regularly use Python for data extraction, processing, analysis, and output. This includes advanced features; such as clustering, optimisation, multi-dimensional arrays, graphs and networks, and data visualisation; on datasets consisting of millions of data points.

Command-line interface

I have experience in Linux and Unix-like operating systems for computational work and automation. This includes the use of Bash, ssh, Git to version control source code, Vim for advanced text editing, and many other CLI tools.

High-performance computing

My PhD studies involved extensive use of a variety of National supercomputing facilities requiring tools such as Slurm (Simple Linux Utility for Resource Management) and PBS (Portable Batch System). Over the course of my research the cumulative computation from these calculations were in the order of 7.4 million CPU hours, resulting in terabytes of data.

Web development

As a Senior Test Analyst my work required an understanding of front end technology and back end technology. I have also created web pages to make the software tools of my PhD research publicly available; these are accessible at atb.uq.edu.au/asp and atb.uq.edu.au/peg. I have also used the Django web-development framework for personal projects.

Digital multimedia

I have a broad skillset using computers for a range of tasks including word processing, spreadsheets, and presentations using the Microsoft Office suite, and creating and editing raster and vector based images using the Adobe suite. I have also used multimedia tools for 2D and 3D animation.

COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT

UNIQUEST RESEARCH COMMERCIALISATION WORKSHOP

Brisbane, Qld July 23 – 24 2019 Took part in two-day workshop focusing on the process of bringing inventions to market, industry engagement, intellectual property management, and research commercialisation models.

ABACBS/COMBINE MEMBER OF ORGANISING COMMITTEE FOR COMBINE SYMPOSIUM

Brisbane, Qld June – Nov 2016 Helped organize and run the COMBINE Symposium for students and early career researchers. Duties included logistics, graphic design, operational tasks, providing assistance to delegates, and chairing the careers panel.

OPEN HEALTH HACK 2015 (BRISBANE)

KNOWLEDGE FOUNDATION

Volunteered at the Brisbane chapter of Health Hack 2015 to assist Karmen Condic-Jurkic in recruiting participants to the project for a molecular dynamics repository. Project was awarded 2nd place prize for \$2000 worth of legal services and counselling.

Brisbane, Qld Oct 2015

PYCON PYTHON CONFERENCE AU 2015

Brisbane, Qld Aug 2015 Volunteered as an organiser at PyCon AU 2015.

ROTARY ROTARY YOUTH LEADERSHIP AWARDS (RYLA)

Brisbane, Qld May 2006 May 2005 RYLA is a youth leadership development program to promote personal and professional development including topics on public speaking, goal setting, interpersonal skills and more. Attended in 2005 as a participant and in 2006 as a volunteer team leader.

REFEREES

UNIVERSITY OF PROF. ALAN E. MARK

QUEENSLAND

Principal Investigator of Molecular Dynamics Group, School of Chemistry & Molecular

Brisbane, Qld Biosciences. Supervisor for PhD.

UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND

Brisbane, Qld

ASSOC. PROF. MIKAEL BODEN

Program Director of Bioinformatics, School of Chemistry & Molecular Biosciences. Cosupervisor for my PhD and coordinator during Masters of Bioinformatics.

WALTER & ELIZA DR. MELISSA DAVIS
HALL INSTITUTE

Joint Head, Division of Bioinformatics, Walter & Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research.

Melbourne, Vic Mentor and research project owner during Masters of Bioinformatics.

UNIVERSITY OF DR. DAVID POGER

QUEENSLAND

Senior Research Fellow in Molecular Dynamics Group, School of Chemistry & Molecular Biosciences. Work colleague and mentor during PhD.

Contact details of referees available on request.